

PROGRAMMER ANALYST

Uluberia, Howrah -711316

🛮 (+91) 7003190619 | 🗷 soumitra.banerjee@hotmail.com | 🏕 soumitrabanerjee.github.io/ | 🗖 soumitra-banerjee/

Summary.

Current Big Data Engineer at IT giant Cognizant with 1.2+ years of professional experience specializing in development and deployment of big data components via Spark, Hadoop, Hive, Scala technologies. Excellent planning skills in setting and achieving goals, including meeting tight deadlines. Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks, and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises.

Experience

Cognizant Technology Solutions India Pvt Ltd

Pune, India

PROGRAMMER ANALYST (DATA ENGINEER)

Sep. 2020 - Present

- Building a Java program to help solve internal problem for comparing data from different environments (Dev, QA and Prod).
- Working on API Gateway based data source for revamping the business logic for user operation on PRTS data from upstream system to Rest API layer using Scala code.
- Worked on Bug Fixing on Spark SQL scripts.
- Worked on Reverse Engineering by backtracking the Database objects from Downstream Systems till Upstream Systems to ensure proper data flow between different layers of the systems.

Cognizant Technology Solutions India Pvt Ltd

Pune, India

INTERN

Jan. 2020 - Apr. 2020

- Trained on Data Warehouse Under Cognizant Trainers' supervision and learnt SQL, Databases, Core-JAVA, OLAP Concept.
- Built a small OOPs based java application to store books detials.

Skills

Big Data Tools Hadoop, Spark, Hive, PySpark

Programming Experienced: Java, Python | Familiar: Scala

Languages Fluent: English, Hindi, Bengali

Education

University of Engineering and Management, Kolkata

Kolkata,India

B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering

Jul. 2016 - Jun. 2020

• Graduated with a DGPA of 8.95

Sri Chaitanya Techno School(CBSE)

HIGHER SECONDARY (10 + 2)

Visakhapatnam,India

• Passed with overall aggregate 76.20%

Meghalaya,India

CMCL Vidya Bharati School(CBSE)

mataya,mata

2016

SECONDARY

• Passed with overall aggregate 85.50%

2014

Extracurricular Activity

- Received "Working as One" award from Cognizant upon successful completion and smooth delivery of previous project.
- Built small projects in college on web application using HTML, PHP, MySQL, CSS.
- Participated in North-East regional science exhibiton held in Guwahati.
- Gained expertise in testing, especially targeted on big data application and business features.
- Participated in India's largest canvas painting held in Guwahati.